Sterling Prize collection
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Sterling Prize collection
1993 - 2003
F-175
Q106660656
13 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Archives and Records Management Department
The University Archives acquires, preserves and makes available three categories of materials: (1) the official records of the University, including those created by the Board of Governors, Senate, University committees, faculties, departments and administrative offices; (2) materials documenting the wider University community; and (3) historical research collections that promote the teaching and research activities of the University.
The Archives was established within the University Library in 1968 when librarian Liisa Fagerlund was appointed University Archivist on a half-time basis. She continued in this post until 1975 when she left the University. From 1975 to 1978, the Archives functioned within the Special Collections division of the Library. Archival duties were carried out by various library staff members. In 1978, the University Archives was established as a separate administrative unit outside of the Library. Donald Baird, recently retired as University Librarian, became University Archivist and held this position until his retirement in 1990. Jim Ross served as University Archivist from 1991 to 1993, and was succeeded by Ian Forsyth in 1994.
When the Archives was a function of the University Library, the University Archivist reported to the University Librarian. When the Archives was established as a separate administrative unit, the University Archivist reported directly to the University President. The reporting structure changed in 1986 when the University Archivist reported to the Vice-President, Research/Information Systems; in 1990, when the University Archivist reported to the Associate Vice-President, Academic; and in 1996, when the University Archivist reported to the Registrar/Dean of Students.
published
Full
Revised
Archivist created title from name of prize.
The Archives established the Sterling Prize Collection in 2000 at the suggestion of Professor Ted Sterling, who, with his wife Nora, established the Sterling Prize for Controversy in 1993. According to the terms of reference for the prize, it may be given for work in any field including—but not limited to—fine arts, humanities, social sciences, natural sciences, and education. The primary aim of the prize is to encourage daring, creative, controversial, unconventional, and non-traditional work at SFU that also meets high standards and is morally and ethically sound. An ancillary aim is to encourage the study, at SFU, of the role of the controversial. The prize is normally awarded to a member of the SFU community—students, faculty, staff, or alumni. The winner is selected by the Sterling Prize Committee, composed of faculty. student and staff representatives.
Dr. Sterling, Professor Emeritus at SFU, was the founder of the University’s computing science program in 1973, and is an expert in computational epidemiology and the social implications of computing. He was awarded an honorary degree by SFU in 2001.
For further information on Ted and Nora Sterling and the Sterling Prize, see the file "Background Information."
In 2000, the archivist asked each previous Sterling Prize winner to give the Archives a copy of his or her Sterling Prize lecture. Some winners were able to supply a prepared text; other winners spoke from notes and supplied these. The archivist added more information to the files including announcements, press releases, articles from Simon Fraser News, print-outs from the Sterling Prize website, (http://www.sfu.ca/sterlingprize/) and other documents. SFU Media and Public Relations gave the Archives a cassette copy of Russel Ogden’s lecture for 1995. Please note that there was no prize winner for 1996.
For a list of speakers included in the collection, see Access Points.
Files arranged by the archivist.
Sterling, Nora; Sterling, Ted; Copes, Parzival; Ogden, Russel; John Lowman; Winston, Mark; Fattah, Ezzat A.; Kimura, Doreen; Mauser, Gary; Crawford, Charles; Punja, Zamir
Created by the Archives in 2000.
Further accruals are expected.
See website, http://www.sfu.ca/sterlingprize/.
A file list is available.
- Background information and prize winners, 1993 - 2003; F-175-1; 13 cm of textual records One cassette
  published
  Contains terms of reference for the Sterling Prize materials and individual files on each prize winner.
  - Background information, 1993 - 2002; F-175-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Parzival Copes, 1994; F-175-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Russel Ogden, 1995; F-175-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - John Lowman, 1997; F-175-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Mark Winston, 1998; F-175-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Ezzat Fattah, 1999; F-175-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Doreen Kimura, 2000; F-175-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Gary Mauser, 2001; F-175-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Charles Crawford, 2002; F-175-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 175-1)
  - Zamir Punja, 2003; F-175-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 175-1)